Hello everybody today's daf is פ"ב Pay Bet 82A and we're at
the top of פ"ב Pay Bet three lines down שיהיה רבי עקיבא
אומר. sheyehei Rebbe Akiva omer. So there's a debate in the משנה
Mishna which is the Torah says any חטאת Chatat that you bring
from its blood פנימה אל הקודש פנימה לכפר בקודש לא תאכל באש
תשרף. pnima el hakodesh pnima lechaper bakodesh lo teachel ba'esh tisaref. You
bring it inside to atone so in the you know היכל Heichal
or the דביר Dvir then it shall not be eaten it shall
be burned. So at one level the פסוק Pasuk is just telling
you that
there's a category called חטאות פנימיות, Chataot Pnimiot, inner חטאות, Chataot, which
is like the פר העלם דבר של ציבור, Par He'elam Davar Shel
Tzibur, the פר par of you know the things that are brought
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and so on and the הלכה halacha
there is explicitly that's the מצוה mitzvah of it you sprinkle the
blood and then you burn the meat outside of the מקדש. Mikdash.
However it's read to mean that also a kosher חטאת Chatat an
outer חטאת Chatat whose blood was brought inside that invalidates it and
it has to be burned and it has to be destroyed and
then the question in the משנה Mishna is is that limited to
a חטאת? Chatat? So רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva says it applies to
all sacrifices if you bring their blood on the inside you invalidate
them they have to be burned and רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer says
well no it's basically a חטאת Chatat but רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer
going back way back to the first משנה mishna of the מסכת
masechet says an אשם asham is like a חטאת chatat so it
would be about an אשם asham as well. So let's take a
look now the גמרא Gemara is going to show you where they
get this from. Three lines from the top of פ"ב עמוד א'.
Pay Bet Amud Aleph. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel משל למה הדבר
דומה Mashal Lema HaDavar Domeh what is this like רבי עקיבא Rebbe
Akiva because what the point is going to be that the פסוק
Pasuk is talking about a חטאת Chatat and then it says any
חטאת Chatat that you bring the blood on the inside so just
say if you bring the blood on the inside why does it
have to say any חטאת Chatat in the context in the Torah
they're talking about a חטאת? Chatat? Okay so it says what is
this like? משל למה הדבר דומה Mashal Lema HaDavar Domeh תלמיד שמזג
לרבו בחמין talmid shemazag lerabo bechamin a תלמיד talmid poured for his
master mixed the wine with hot water. We had this משל mashal
earlier. Right. Okay. Right. ואמר לו מזוג לי V'amar lo mezog li
and so he was already you know he had poured to him
right before he had mixed his wine with hot water and then
the master said oh could you please mix me some more wine.
אמר לו במה Amar lo bema what would you like me to
mix it with hot water or cold water? אמר לו לא בחמין
אנו עסקין? Amar lo lo bechamin anu askin? עסוקין? Osukin? What do
you mean we've been dealing you've been mixing it with hot water
until now. I don't have to say hot water you should just
figure it out. Okay. עכשיו בין בחמין בין בצונן. Achshav bein bechamin
bein betzonen. You know now that you're bothering me to say explicitly
whatever you know it was already implicit that it'll be fine do
it if you want to do with cold water too. Okay. So
let's see what the נמשל nimshal is. הכא נמי מכדי בחטאת עסקינן.
Hacha nami meichti bechatat askinan.
In the context where the Torah was talking about if you bring
the blood on the inside it was already talking about a חטאת.
chatat. Okay. חטאת דכתב רחמנא למה לי? Chatat dechtav Rachmana lamah li?
Why did it say וכל חטאת אשר יובא מדמה אל אהל מועד
אל הקודש פנימה לא תאכל? Vechol Chatat Asher Yuva Midamah El Ohel
Moed El Hakodesh Pnima Lo Te'achel? It just should have said וכל
אשר יובא מדמה Vechol Asher Yuva Midamah because the context the context
was a חטאת. chatat. Okay so since like the story before when
you just asked for mixing the wine silence would have been implicit
to mean hot water because that's what it was being talked about.
So here too the silence would have been implicit to mean a
חטאת. chatat. So now that you want now so if we're going
to go out and not be silent and say something okay so
אלא לאו חטאת קאמי לא אלא כל קדשים. ela lav chatat kami
lo ela kol kodshim. When it says חטאת chatat it doesn't mean
only חטאת chatat it means all קדשים. kodshim.
So that's not so helpful because in the משל mashal right the
master says fine you didn't have to ask you're asking all right
whatever you want to use cold water use cold water too but
he says cold water. If the master said you didn't have to
ask hot water then it would have meant hot water. So even
though the Torah didn't have to say חטאת chatat it would have
been implicit by saying חטאת chatat it's not clear why that includes
things other than a חטאת chatat so don't really exactly get the
משל. mashal. But somehow the point was חטאת chatat was implicit by
saying חטאת chatat it's meant to include even more. But how do
you know that invalidates everything it's supposed to just say like once
you do it you know you can't make it up and you
know and then if you do somehow you can't you still can't
eat the meat. Like how do we know it's just a הלכה
halacha of meat and not an invalidating I don't know that's a
good question I don't know. Okay אלא כל קדשים. ela kol kodshim.
So מתקיף לה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע Maskif la Rav Huna
Brey de Rav Yehoshua so רב הונא Rav Huna challenged this. מכדי
איתרבו כל קדשים לגבי מזבח לענין מריקה ושטיפה. Meichti israbo kol kodshim
legabei mizbe'ach linyan merika ushtifa. So he says you're it's not correct
the immediate context was not just that of a חטאת chatat because
the פסוקים psukim right before Michael do you have the פסוקים? psukim?
Yeah I'm just trying to get this it's 82. Yeah so the
פסוקים psukim right before is a cycle so it says like this:
וידבר ה' אל משה Vayedaber Hashem el Moshe so this is in
צו. Tzav. דבר אל אהרן ואל בניו לאמר זאת תורת החטאת Daber
el Aharon v'el banav lemor Zot Torat HaChatat so the big rubric
is חטאת Chatat right. במקום אשר תשחט העלה תשחט החטאת לפני ה'
קדש קדשים הוא. Bimkom asher tishachet ha'olah tishachet hachatat lifnei Hashem Kodesh
Kodashim hu. הכהן המחטא אתה יאכלנה במקום קדש תאכל בחצר אהל מועד...
Hakohen hamekate ota yochelena bemakom kadosh te'achel bechatzar ohel moed... eat it
in the חצר אהל מועד. chatzar ohel moed. Now
before you get to this thing about the blood inside it says:
כל אשר יגע בבשרה יקדש ואשר יזה מדמה אל הבגד אשר יזה
עליה תכבס במקום קדוש. Kol asher yiga bivsarah yikdash va'asher yizeh midamah
el habeged asher yizeh aleha techabes bemakom kadosh. If the blood gets
on something it gets sanctified you have to cleanse it. וכלי חרש
אשר תבשל בו ישבר, uchli cheres asher tevushel bo yishaver, if you
use it to cook, to cook, then I mean this is like
one of the basis for the idea that vessels absorb taste and
they're a problem or whatever. So the vessel that you use, the
pottery vessel at least absorbs the taste of the חטאת chatat and
then by the next morning the taste inside is going to be
נותר nosar because the חטאת chatat would be נותר nosar by the
next morning, so you can't use this pot again, so you have
to break it. ואם בכלי נחושת בשלה, ve'im bichli nechoshet bushalah, if
it's copper, so you don't have to break it, there's a way
of kashering it, ומרק
ושטף במים. umorak veshutaf bamayim. So you put it scalding water, cold
water, so this is basically like a good basis for the idea
of kashering. Oh, ומרק, umorak, you're saying means scalding water, you said,
I heard you say that? Yeah. Okay, scoured and rinsed with water
is how the English translates it. Okay, then it says, וכל חטאת
אשר יובא מדמה אל אהל מועד לכפר בקדש לא תאכל באש תשרף.
vechol chatat asher yuva midamah el ohel mo'ed lechaper bakodesh lo te'achel
ba'esh tisaref.
So now the point is, on one hand the point is the
whole context here is חטאת. chatat. So why did it say חטאת,
chatat, it must be coming to include. But the counter-argument is going
to be this הלכה halacha that immediately preceded it, that if the
vessel you used to cook it absorbs the tastes and you have
to kasher the vessel and so on, in a different גמרא Gemara
we learn that that הלכה halacha is not limited to a חטאת.
chatat. That הלכה halacha applies to all קרבנות. korbanot. So actually, says
the גמרא, Gemara, the immediate context is not limited to a חטאת,
chatat, and therefore by saying חטאת chatat it had to say חטאת
chatat and it means specifically חטאת. chatat. Okay, so it says like
this. So מכדי, michdi, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, מכדי
אישתרא בכל קדשים לגבי מזבח דאין מריקה ושטיפה, michdi ishtara bechol kodashim
legabei mizbeach de'ein merika ushfifa, in another place we learn that the
earlier פסוק pasuk that talks about scalding it and rinsing it by
a pot that it was cooked with does not apply just to
a חטאת, chatat, that applies to all sacrifices. So חטאת דכתב רחמנא
למה לי, chatat dechativ rachmana lama li, so when it got to
saying חטאת chatat by bringing the blood on the inside, it's not
being redundant, actually it's being limiting. שמע מינה חטאת אין מידי אחריני
לא, shma mina chatat in midei achrini lo, only a חטאת. chatat.
Okay, so והא דדמיא veha de'damya and therefore what it's really similar,
says back to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or says back to רב
יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel who's trying to defend רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
If you want to know what it's similar, it's similar to לתלמיד
שמזג לרבו בין בחמין בין בצונן, letalmid shemazag lerabbo bein bechamin bein
betzonen, that the תלמיד talmid was mixing wine, sometimes he was using
hot water, sometimes cold water. אמר לו אל תמזג לי אלא חמין
amar lo al timzag li ela chamin and he says please pour
me with hot water. So hot water there means hot water, it
doesn't mean whatever you want. Fine. So you can't say that the
point of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is because the context was already
a חטאת, chatat, so being redundant is meant to include. Because A,
just the idea that being redundant is meant to expand is not
so clear, and B, it's not so redundant because the immediate פסוקים
pesukim might have been talking about a broader scope.
אלא טעמא דרבי עקיבא מחטאת וכל חטאת, ela ta'ama deRabbi Akiva mechatat
vechol chatat, because it could have
said ואשר יובא מחטאת, וכל חטאת, va'asher yuva mechatat, vechol chatat, the
וכל, vechol, that's an expansive word. Now again, you still have the
word חטאת, chatat, but anyway, the word וכל vechol is coming to
include all types of sacrifices. דתניא, detanya, and here we have a
ברייתא braita that says this. חטאת אין לי אלא חטאת קדשי קדשים
מנין, chatat ein li ela chatat kodshei kodashim minayin, how do you
know other קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim like an עולה? olah? תלמוד לומר
וכל חטאת. talmud lomar vechol chatat. אשם, asham, קדשים קלים מנין, kodashim
kalim minayin, how do you know even something like a שלמים? shlamim?
תלמוד לומר וכל, talmud lomar vechol, and then the extra ו vav
חטאת. chatat. דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. Okay, so it's based
on the extra word וכל vechol that expands it. אמר לו רבי
יוסי הגלילי, amar lo Rabbi Yossi HaGlili, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi
HaGlili said back to him, אפילו אתה מרבה כל היום כולו איני
שומע לך, afilu ata marbe kol hayom kulo eini shomea lach, even
if you try to, this is the classic רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi debate,
which is that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva always tries to learn from
every little extra letter, extra word, a whole big thing and רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili says to him, you could try to
fit as much as you want into those little extra words, extra
letters, I don't buy any of that.
אפילו אתה מרבה כל היום כולו איני שומע לך, afilu ata marbe
kol hayom kulo eini shomea lach, I'm not buying it. אלא חטאת.
ela chatat. Here's what, now the funny thing is, it's not like
he rejects the idea that the word וכל vechol is coming to
include. But what he rejects is a forced read of the verse,
like he's like a דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. dibra torah kilshon
bnei adam. So to say the word וכל חטאת vechol chatat means
that it doesn't have to be a חטאת chatat is a bit
of a force. To say וכל vechol is coming to include more
things, that I'll buy. But to say it's coming to include things
that aren't a חטאת chatat when the פסוק pasuk says any חטאת,
chatat, that I'm not going to buy. So what is וכל vechol
coming to include? אלא חטאת אין לי אלא חטאת יחיד, ela chatat
ein li ela chatat yachid, I only know it applies to an
individual חטאת chatat because that's the general context here. חטאת ציבור מנין,
chatat tzibur minayin, תלמוד לומר וכל חטאת, talmud lomar vechol chatat, any
חטאת. chatat. So yes, וכל vechol is including, but it's including a
wider range of חטאות. chataot. It's not including something that isn't a
חטאת. chatat. ואין לי אלא חטאת זכר, ve'ein li ela chatat zachar,
I only know a male חטאת. chatat. Why? Well, that we're going
to get to in a minute. חטאת נקבה מנין, chatat nekeva minayin,
תלמוד לומר וכל, talmud lomar vechol, the extra ו. vav. So it's
including all forms of חטאת, chatat, but it's only including חטאת. chatat.
So now the גמרא Gemara says כלפי לייא, klapi laya, like where's
this going? What do you mean? Oh, I only know a male,
how do I know a female? The standard חטאת chatat is female.
Okay. אלא הכי קאמר, ela hachi ka'amar, you're right, reverse it. אין
לי אלא חטאת נקבה, ein li ela chatat nekeva, I would only
know a female חטאת, chatat, which is like the vast majority. חטאת
זכר מנין, chatat zachar minayin, how do I know a male? תלמוד
לומר וכל. talmud lomar vechol. So wait, where would you have a
חטאת זכר chatat zachar that's not already included in a, the שעיר...
se'ir... the שעיר sa'ir for נשיא. nasi. הא, Ha, no, but I'm
saying, but he's saying, oh, but that's not considered a חטאת ציבור,
chatat tzibur, right? That's a... Okay. וסבר רבי יוסי הגלילי, V'savar Rebbe
Yose HaGlili, good question. וסבר רבי יוסי הגלילי האי קרא להכי הוא
דאתא? V'savar Rebbe Yose HaGlili hai kra l'hachi hu d'ata? Okay, anyway,
so רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yose HaGlili says וכל v'chol is coming
to include a wider range of חטאות, chata'ot, but I'm not buying
רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, how you can get a word there and
say it doesn't mean חטאת. chatat. Anyway, now וסבר רבי יוסי הגלילי
האי קרא להכי הוא דאתא? v'savar Rebbe Yose HaGlili hai kra l'hachi
hu d'ata? Does he think that's what the פסוק pasuk is? והתניא
רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר כל הענין כולו אינו מדבר אלא בפרים הנשרפים
ושעירים הנשרפים לשרוף פסוליהם על בית הבירה ולעמוד בלא תעשה על אכילתו.
V'hatanya Rebbe Yose HaGlili omer kol ha'inyan kulo eino medaber ella b'farim
hanisrafim u'se'irim hanisrafim lisrof psuleihem al Beit HaBirah v'la'amod b'lo ta'aseh al
achilato. He says actually, like I was telling you before, this פסוק
pasuk has nothing to do with invalidating a חטאת. chatat. This is
telling you that there is a category called חטאות פנימיות, chata'ot pnimiyot,
inner חטאות, chata'ot, and it's telling you not that you invalidated it
by bringing the blood. This is what you're supposed to do, and
if you bring the blood on the inside, so then you go
ahead and you know, you go ahead and you burn. Now, actually,
I'm a little, now, the point is though that actually, so no,
it's not exactly what I was saying, because what I was saying
is is that then it's talking that you did it properly. And
this says לשרוף את פסוליהם, lisrof es psuleihem, when it becomes פסול.
pasul. I just want to check רש"י, Rashi, hold on a
minute.
Right, meaning like this, so that if, although it's a funny way
of reading the פסוק, pasuk, it's saying if you're dealing with a
חטאת פנימית, chatat pnimis, an inner חטאת, chatat, one that
אשר יובא מדמה אל הקודש פנימה, asher yuva midamah el ha'kodesh pnimah,
but, and here's the big but what it's reading into it, but
something, now what happens by a normal inner חטאת? chatat? Where do
you burn it? You burn it outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
Here's the irony, that's if you're doing it properly, right? So a
normal inner חטאת, chatat, the way you do the מצוה mitzvah is
you burn the meat outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. What happens
if some פסול psul happened? I don't know, turns out that it
was a בעל מום. ba'al mum. It turns out that a כהן
kohen had a thought of שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah, okay? So where
do you burn it? You burn it, but you know where you
burn it? In the עזרה. Azarah. That's bizarre, that's called the בית
הבירה Beit HaBirah is where you burn it in the עזרה. Azarah.
So somehow he's reading this verse to be talking only about an
inner חטאת, chatat, אשר יובא מדמה, asher yuva midamah, but somehow you
have to read into the verse, oh, and something happened to invalidate
it, then לא תאכל באש תשרף, lo te'achel ba'esh tisaref, like don't
eat it, burn it, burn it in a fire, but burn it
in a fire in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, okay? So that's
what it's talking about. אינו מדבר אלא בפרים הנשרפים ושעירים הנשרפים לשרוף
פסוליהם על בית הבירה, Eino medaber ella b'farim hanisrafim u'se'irim hanisrafim lisrof
psuleihem al Beit HaBirah, so one חידוש chidush it's telling you is
is that if an invalidity happens, don't burn it out of the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, burn it in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
And the second point it's telling you is ולעמוד בלא תעשה על
אכילתו. v'la'amod b'lo ta'aseh al achilato. It's to tell you לא תאכל,
lo te'achel, it's to tell you that you actually will violate, because
before it was an עשה, aseh, right? Exactly, it's not just an
עשה, aseh, you would violate if you would eat the meat of
an inner חטאת. chatat. But basically the פסוק pasuk is focused on
the inner חטאת, chatat, not on some outer חטאת, chatat, okay? So
that's what he says the פסוק pasuk is. So what's he doing
debating with רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva וכל חטאת v'chol chatat to talk
about other types of חטאות? chata'ot? He doesn't say it's talking about
an outer חטאת chatat at all. He says it's only talking about
an inner חטאת. chatat. So the גמרא Gemara says אמרו לו חטאת
שנכנס דמה לפנים מניין? amru lo chatat shenichnas damah lifnim minayin? אמר
להן הן לא הובא. amar lahen hen lo huva.
So okay, they said to him, that's very nice, that's what you
want to say that פסוק pasuk is talking about, but you don't
disagree with the general הלכה halachah that an outer חטאת chatat is
invalidated? So where do you get that הלכה halachah that a general
חטאת chatat is invalidated when you bring the blood on the inside?
So he says, oh, I get that from the whole story by
משה Moshe and אהרן Aharon and the חטאת chatat that was burned,
because משה Moshe says to אהרן, Aharon, why did you burn it?
הן לא הובא את דמה אל הקודש פנימה, Hen lo huva es
damah el ha'kodesh pnimah, and you didn't bring the blood on the
inside, which is implicit, had you brought the blood on the inside,
I would have understood why you had to burn it, okay? So
that's where I get it from. From that story of משה Moshe
and אהרן Aharon I get the idea that it's invalidated when you
bring the blood on the inside. Okay, but from, but from this
פסוק, pasuk, that's only telling you that there's a לאו, lav, it's
telling you that if it gets
invalidated of an inner חטאת, chatat, if it gets invalidated you burn
it in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So anyway, לדבריו דרבי עקיבא
קאמר. l'dvarav d'Rebbe Akiva ka'amar. Fine, when he was pushing back on
רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva he says look, as far as I'm concerned,
this פסוק pasuk וכל חטאת v'chol chatat has nothing to do with
an outer חטאת, chatat, it's only about an inner חטאת. chatat. You
want to read it as about an outer חטאת chatat and and
therefore you're going to say it does not limit it to a
חטאת, chatat, it applies to an עולה olah and שלמים shelamim or
whatever, based on the word וכל, v'chol, I'm going to tell you
back, according to your read of it, that it's talking about an
outer קרבן, korban, it's still not legitimate to read it about anything
other than a חטאת. chatat. So I don't read it about an
outer קרבן. korban. My idea of the outer קרבן korban being invalidated
I learn from the משה Moshe and אהרן Aharon story. I read
this about an inner חטאת. chatat. But you, רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva,
that read it about an outer קרבן, korban, you have no basis
of extending it beyond the חטאת, chatat, okay? So that's the question,
does it go just to a חטאת chatat or even to an
אשם asham or even to all קרבנות? korbanot? Next משנה. mishnah. But
do we usually פסק pasken like רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva anyway? No,
only מחבירו michaveiro not מחביריו. michaveirav. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, חטאת שקיבל דמה. chatat shekibel damah. Now we're going
to, since we've introduced this question about invalidating a חטאת chatat that's
blood is brought on the inside, we're going to now explore the
different scenarios in which that blood, in which that happens. קרבן korban
would be invalidated. So, חטאת שקיבל דמה בשני כוסות. Chatat shekibel damah
bishnei kossot. You caught the blood in two, you know, I'm going
to say bowls, it always says a כוס, kos, but like, if
you have blood squirting out of an animal's neck, I wouldn't want
a bowl, I would not want a, like a glass. Anyway, okay,
you caught its blood into two bowls, and יצא אחד מהם לחוץ.
yatza echad meihem lachutz. One of them is brought outside the בית
המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So that blood becomes invalid. Does the קרבן korban
become invalid? Well, I think you'd have enough, so the משנה Mishna
says, no, the קרבן korban is still valid, it only invalidates the
blood, not the קרבן, korban, and if there's enough leftover good blood,
you can bring it on the מזבח mizbe'ach and you're fine. Okay.
אחד מהם לחוץ, הפנימי כשר. Echad meihem lachutz, hapnimi kasher. The inner
one is כשר. kasher. נכנס אחד מהם לפנימה. Nichnas echad meihem lifnimah.
Now let's say half of the blood gets brought inside the היכל.
Heichal. This, this inner, this brought on the, you know, inner, which
is what we've been talking about until now. רבי יוסי הגלילי מכשיר
בחיצון. Rabbi Yose HaGlili machshir bchitzon. He says it's actually valid. וחכמים
פוסלים. Vachachamim poslin. And the חכמים Chachamim invalidate. Now, רש״י Rashi is
going, and he's making a difference which one he's brought first? No,
no, no. So רש״י Rashi is going to say, I mean the
גמרא Gemara is going to say this, but רש״י, Rashi, it's a
very nice רש״י. Rashi. רש״י Rashi actually says this actually ties back
to which פסוק pasuk they learn it from, because the חכמים Chachamim
say how do we know that when an outer חטאת's Chatat blood
is brought inside it invalidates? It says וכל חטאת אשר יובא מדמה
אל הקדש פנימה. Vechol chatat asher yuva midamah el hakodesh penimah. Some
of its blood is brought inside, it invalidates. מדמה Midamah means even
some of its blood. So that's why the חכמים Chachamim say even
if only some of the blood is brought inside it invalidates. But
רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, where does he get it from?
When משה Moshe says to אהרן, Aharon, הן לא הובא את דמה
אל הקדש פנימה. Hen lo huva et damah el hakodesh penimah. So
it doesn't say מדמה midamah but את דמה. et damah. So for
יוסי הגלילי, Yose HaGlili, he learns it from a פסוק pasuk that
speaks about bringing all of the blood on the inside, whereas the...
this is all in רש״י, Rashi, it's not in the גמרא. Gemara.
Whereas the... whereas the חכמים Chachamim learn it from the word מדמה
midamah means even some of the blood, and therefore the whole קרבן's
korban invalid. So I'm trying to understand this. Let's say I first
brought it outside, right, and the blood is מכפר mechaper and I
brought my שיעור shiur of the blood. Then aren't I done? Now
are we saying retroactively I wasn't good? No. No, no, no, it's
a different scenario. Scenario one is you brought the first... you have
two כוסות, kossot, one and two. Scenario one is you brought כוס
kos one out of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. The הלכה halacha
is use blood two on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Exactly. Different scenario, that's
scenario A. Scenario B, you brought כוס kos one into the היכל.
Heichal. The הלכה halacha is whole קרבן's korban invalid. No, but that's
not my question. My question is you haven't thrown the blood yet.
No, but let's say you had two כוסות, kossot, you brought the
first one on the properly and you brought the second one in
the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, I mean in the עזרה, azarah, then
you're fine. Then you're fine, yes. It's only... it's only when you...
when it has not yet been validated that it invalidates. Fine. Okay.
Got it. אמר רבי יוסי הגלילי. Amar Rabbi Yose HaGlili. So now
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili is going to challenge the חכמים,
Chachamim, because the irony according to the חכמים Chachamim is that the
inside has more power to invalidate than the outside, right? That's... right?
Because the outside, according to the חכמים, Chachamim, partial blood, the blood's
invalid but the קרבן korban is not. The inside, some of the
blood, it invalidates the whole קרבן. korban. So that's a little ironic
that the inside has a more powerful to invalidate than the outside.
Okay, so that's what he's going to say. אמר רבי יוסי הגלילי
מה במקום שהמחשבה פוסלת, Amar Rabbi Yose HaGlili mah bemakom shehamachshava poselet,
the place where if you had a thought to bring the קרבן,
korban, right, this is going back, you never get away from פיגול,
piggul, right, or חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano or whatever or חוץ למקומו.
chutz limkomo. So this is חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, not exactly פיגול.
piggul. If you had a thought to bring the קרבן חוץ למקומו,
korban chutz limkomo, to bring it outside the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash,
your thought alone would invalidate. So that's... so מה במקום שהמחשבה פוסלת,
mah bemakom shehamachshava poselet, where does thought invalidate? If thought is directed
to what place? בחוץ, Bachutz, if the thought is directed to the
outside. לא עשה את המשויר כיוצא. Lo asa et hamishuyar kiyotze. So
the remainder blood does not get invalidated by the blood that is
brought to the outside, even though the outside is a very powerfully
invalidating place, even thoughts about the outside invalidate. So מקום שאין המחשבה
פוסלת, makom she'ein hamachshava poselet, the place where thoughts do not invalidate,
בפנים, bifnim, if you think about bringing the blood in the היכל,
Heichal, that does not make the קרבן korban invalid, your thought directed
to the inside does not invalidate. So if that's true, the inside
is not as invalidating of a place. So if that's true, אינו
דין שלא נעשה המשויר כנכנס? eino din shelo na'aseh hamishuyar kenichnas? Shouldn't
we say certainly that if you bring some blood, the remainder blood
should not be invalid? If the remainder blood is invalid when you
brought it on the outside, which is a bigger problem, shouldn't it
not be invalid when you bring some of the blood on the
inside?
So... אינו דין שלא נעשה המשויר כנכנס. eino din shelo na'aseh hamishuyar
kenichnas. Now, so we don't hear an answer, okay? That's a pretty...
his pretty strong argument, this is ironic. Next point: נכנס לכפר אף
על פי שלא כיפר פסול דברי רבי אליעזר. Nichnas lechaper af al
pi shelo chiper passul divrei Rabbi Eliezer. Let's say you brought the
blood to the inside for the sake of putting it on the
inner altar, but you never got around to putting it on the
inner altar, because the פסוק pasuk says אשר יובא מדמה אל הקדש
לכפר בקדש. asher yuva midamah el hakodesh lechaper bakodesh. You do it
for the sake of atoning. But does it mean what... but let's
say that was your intent, but you never actually did it. Okay?
So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that invalidates. רבי שמעון אומר עד
שיכפר. Rabbi Shimon omer ad sheyichaper. No, it means you did it
for that sake and you actually put it on the inner altar
or on the פרוכת parochet or whatever you did, some blood ritual
on the inside. Bringing it on the inside with that intent, without
actually doing some atonement... fine. atonement ritual does not invalidate. רבי יהודה
אומר אם הכניס שוגג כשר. Rabbi Yehuda omer im hichnis shogeg kasher.
It's only if you did it unintentionally then it's כשר kasher because
again he reads לכפר בקודש. lechaper bakodesh. Now what does שוגג shogeg
mean? שוגג shogeg means you didn't realize you had some blood in
your vessel? Does שוגג shogeg mean you thought it was inner blood,
you didn't realize it was outer blood? Okay, so we'll have to
see. But again focusing on the fact that the verse emphasizes your
intent, אשר הובא מדמה
לכפר בקודש. asher huva midama lechaper bakodesh. Okay. Now כל הדמים פסולים
שנתנו על גבי המזבח לא הורצו. kol hadamim pesulim shenitnu al gabei
hamizbeach lo hurtzu. Totally different הלכה. halacha. You have invalid blood. How
did the blood become invalid? Some of the blood was brought outside,
let's say. Okay, so let's use that example. Okay, or let's say
it was the blood I don't know of a בעל מום ba'al
mum or whatever it is. Some blood is invalid. Okay, and you
went ahead and you put it anyway on the altar, the outer
altar. This is a completely different הלכה. halacha. We are now no
longer talking about the הלכה halacha of blood on the inside. Different
הלכה. halacha. Blood that became invalid and you put it on the
altar. So even though we have a principle that sometimes invalid things
that are put on the altar stay on the altar, that doesn't
mean the קרבן korban becomes כשר. kasher. So if you put blood
on the altar that didn't belong there, maybe you don't have to
I don't know scrape it off, like the same way if you
put limbs that don't belong you don't take them down, but it
doesn't mean the קרבן korban is valid, becomes valid. לא הרצה הציץ.
lo hirtza hatzitz. The ציץ tzitz does not validate it. אלא על
הטמא. ela al hatamei. The only thing the ציץ tzitz makes valid,
right, is טומאת הקדשים. tumat hakodashim. That if the blood is טמא
tamei and you put it on the altar, then the presence of
the ציץ tzitz actually makes the קרבן korban a kosher קרבן. korban.
שהציץ מרצה על הטמא ואינו מרצה על היוצא. shehatzitz mertze al hatamei
ve'eino mertze al hayotze. Since we dealt with blood going outside, blood
that went outside put on the altar, the קרבן korban is no
good. Blood that became טמא tamei put on the altar, that is
good because of the power of the ציץ. tzitz. Okay, so the
last one is no longer talking about inner blood, it's talking about
other invalidities of blood and the power of the ציץ, tzitz, completely
different point. Yes. So how does this relate to yesterday's discussion about
how the previous שיעור shiur's discussion about considering if it's it was
not the proper blood you just consider it as water?
That's a way that allows you to put it on the altar
and not feel that oh my god I'm not allowed to put
this, it's the wrong place to put it. But that doesn't mean
that if the blood itself is invalid, the קרבן korban to be
כשר, kasher, yesterday we never said anything different than for the קרבן
korban to be כשר kasher the blood has to be כשר kasher
blood and has to get at the right place. We only allowed
you to look at the wrong blood as water so you wouldn't
feel say oh I'm not allowed to put the blood here because
there's some wrong blood going in the wrong place. It's not invalid
blood, it's just the blood that doesn't belong here. So and it
allows me to say I'm going to ignore its presence to allow
me to put the other part of the blood in this place,
you know. Okay, תניא, tanya, we're taught תניא. tanya. אמר רבי יוסי
הגלילי קל וחומר. amar Rabbi Yose HaGlili kal vachomer. So now because
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili is not going to let up
on his point that it's crazy that the inside is more invalidating
than the
outside. Either you should agree to me that it doesn't invalidate, or
if you don't agree to me I'm going to push you to
the absurdity of your conclusions of giving more invalidating weight to the
inside than the outside.
תניא אמר רבי יוסי הגלילי קל וחומר ומה במקום שמחשבה פוסלת
בחוץ לא פסל דם שבחוץ את שבפנים. tanya amar Rabbi Yose HaGlili
kal vachomer u'mah bemakom shemachshava poselet bachutz lo pasal dam shebachutz et
shebifnim. Outside where thought invalidates, meaning if thought is directed to the
outside, nevertheless some of the blood doesn't invalidate the rest of it.
Okay, את שבפנים. et shebifnim. מקום שאין מחשבה פוסלת, makom she'ein machshava
poselet, a place where thought doesn't invalidate if it's directed to it.
בפנים, bifnim, on the inside,
היכל, heichal, אינו דין שלא יפסול דם שבפנים את שבחוץ. eino din
shelo yifsol dam shebifnim et shebachutz. Certainly if you bring blood on
the inside that's a weaker that's not as invalidating of a place,
that shouldn't invalidate the rest of the קרבן. korban. I'm sorry, how's
that different than what he said? Same thing he said in the
משנה mishna except actually said a little clearer here. Okay, but it's
going to be a longer discussion in this ברייתא. braita. אמרו לו,
amru lo, so he said back to him. So הרי הוא אומר,
harei hu omer, the verse says אשר יובא מדמה, asher yuva midama,
אפילו מקצת דמה, afilu miktzat dama, even some of the blood. So
that part of what רש״י Rashi said before is in the גמרא,
Gemara, even some of the blood. But רש״י Rashi says that you
know that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that you know that רבי יוסי׳ס
Rabbi Yose's response back would be I got a different פסוק. pasuk.
I have a פסוק pasuk that says הן לא הובא את דמה.
hen lo huva et dama. Okay, but the חכמים chachamim are sourcing
it in this point of מדמה. midama. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says fine. You want to start by saying even some of the
blood invalidates? But I'm still not giving up on my קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. So then the my next argument should be if some
of the blood invalidates on the inside which is not as bad
of a place, certainly some of the blood on the outside should
invalidate the rest. Because I'm still not giving up on my קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. אמר להם, amar lahem, he said back to them.
קל וחומר ליוצא מעתה. kal vachomer leyotze me'ata. Fine, let's follow your
train of thought and sort of say what would apply to blood
that went on the outside. ומה במקום שמחשבה פוסלת בפנים, u'mah bemakom
shemachshava poselet bifnim,
when it's talking about the inside, היכל, heichal, where thought does not
invalidate, פוסל דם שבפנים את שבחוץ. posel dam shebifnim et shebachutz. So
this weaker place, the inside, is so strong enough to say some
blood that went in there invalidates all the rest. Okay, that's when
it's on the inside.
So
מקום... makom... אמרו לו *amru lo*, they said it
back to
him: הרי אומר אשר יובא *harei omer asher yuvah*, הנכנס פוסל ואין
היוצא פוסל *hanichnas posel ve’ein hayotzei posel*. This הלכה halacha *halacha* of
אשר יובא מדם *asher yuvah midam*, even some of the blood invalidates,
is limited to אשר יובא *asher yuvah* when it’s brought inside. So
they said, "No, it’s a special הלכה halacha *halacha*. You’re right, the
logic doesn’t hold. We’re not arguing with you that it’s rational or
logical why the inside should be more invalidating, but we’re telling you
it’s a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. The פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says מדם *midam*,
even a little bit of blood invalidates inside, and the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* stresses that it is because it’s brought inside. So this הלכה
halacha, *halacha* that even a little invalidates is a דין *din* only
in being brought inside. It is not a דין *din* and it,
you know, it is just being limited to this, and yes, it’s
ironic. It doesn’t apply when a little bit of blood is brought
on the outside. Now, if you want to step back and just
speak a little bit about the logic of this, you do understand
the logic because, well, first of all, let’s just say technically what’s
being said. What’s being said is when blood is brought outside, the
blood becomes invalid. So some blood is invalid, use the rest. When
blood is brought inside, it’s not the הלכה halacha. *halacha* that the
blood becomes invalid. The הלכה halacha, *halacha* is that the קרבן korban,
*korban* becomes invalid. If you bring the blood inside, it’s not because
why should inside invalidate the blood? Like, you know, it’s not you’re
still in the מקדש Mikdash. *mikdash*, it’s right. So it’s actually the
קרבן korban. *korban* is invalid. And there’s a logic because and that’s
why it says if you bring the blood inside לכפר *lechaper* to
atone. Because by bringing it inside to atone, you are basically treating
it like an inner חטאת chatas *chatas*. If you’re going to treat
it like an inner חטאת Chatas. *chatas*, it’s going to get the
status of an inner חטאת chatas, *chatas* and it’s going to have
to basically be burnt outside, you know, outside the מקדש Mikdash, *mikdash*
etc., etc. So, you know, it’s going to have to, well, whatever,
it’s going to have to be burnt, right? So therefore there’s a
logic. Blood on the outside, the blood is invalid, the rest of
the blood is okay. Blood on the inside, you're treating it like
an inner חטאת chatas, *chatas*, the whole קרבן korban. *korban* is invalid.
It's not just the blood is invalid. And that's why even a
little, because by the way, when you bring the blood inside to
actually do the application of blood, you don't bring all the blood
inside, you don't have to, whatever. So it's really the point is
you're doing this ritual and that invalidates the קרבן korban, *korban*. It's
not so much about invalidating the blood. Yes, what do you want
to say? Doesn't invalidate? You don't even it doesn't serve as atone?
Correct. But but if in other words, you can't turn it into
a validated חטאת chatas. *chatas* that you brought in. Correct. Correct. An
inner חטאת chatas *chatas* that the blood is brought inside, the whole
קרבן korban *korban* is invalid. What are you asking? What do you
mean by invalid? You have to burn it, right? You have to
burn it and the owners don't satisfy their obligation.
What's not clear? I see what you're saying. In other words, if
it was to be an inner חטאת *chatas*, then it would be
כשר kasher *kasher*, it would be valid, you just have to burn
it anyway, right?
Yes, right, that's the irony, is that an inner חטאת *chatas* is
valid and you burn it, and an outer חטאת *chatas* that's brought
inside is treated to some degree like an inner חטאת *chatas*, but
it's invalid, right? So that's the so but anyway, but that's the
point. If you're going to treat this like an inner חטאת *chatas*,
that invalidates it. Okay, but it's a דין *din*, it's a הלכה
halacha *halacha* that the קרבן korban, *korban* is invalid, not that somehow
the blood became no, you know, bad because it was brought on
the inside. And that's why it's only in the context of לכפר
בקודש lechaper bakodesh. *lechaper bakodesh*, to doing for the sake of atonement.
But that's what it apply it applies even to a small amount
of blood. You don't need the whole amount of blood. Okay, so
it says like
this. Okay, where were we?
Anyway, the one thing that I was checking, actually, I have to
double check this, but I'm pretty sure is that it's not treated
totally like an inner חטאת *chatas*, because as we said, an inner
חטאת *chatas* the meat is burnt outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash,
*beis hamikdash*, and invalid קרבנות *korbanos* the meat is burnt inside the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *beis hamikdash*. So it's not treated exactly like
an inner חטאת *chatas*. Okay, but anyway, it's basically it's invalid. Okay,
but still what invalidates it is that you are doing the ritual
of an inner חטאת *chatas* to it. And therefore, it's only when
it's done לכפר בקודש *lechaper bakodesh*, but even if it's only some
of the blood. Okay, so that's the basic difference. Okay, תהא מחשבה
בפנים *tehei machshava bifnim*, now the גמרא Gemara *gemara* asks: Okay, now
that we've got this difference, why don't we say the following? Now
that you said that the outer is only partly invalid, but the
inner is totally invalid, תהא מחשבה בפנים פוסלת מקל וחומר *tehei machshava
bifnim poseles mikal vachomer*. Why don't we say, "Okay, so if the
inside is more powerful than the outside, let's now say maybe your
thought the" we were sort of saying there was a difference in
terms of where your thought invalidates. But now that you're showing me
as far as the blood is concerned, the inside... is more invalidating
than the outside, let's say if you have a thought to bring
it on the inside that also invalidates, okay, because the inside is
now more invalidating than the outside. ותימא מחשבה בפנים פוסלת מקל וחומר.
Let that invalidate. ומה במקום שלא פסל דם שבחוץ את שבפנים מחשבה
פוסלת בחוץ, Uma bemakom shelo pasal dam shebachutz es shebifnim machshava poseles
bachutz, where some of the blood doesn't invalidate the rest, thought still
invalidates, i.e., the outside of the מקדש. Mikdash. מקום שפסל דם שבפנים
את דם שבחוץ, Makom shepasal dam shebifnim es dam shebachutz, the place
where some of the blood invalidates the all of it, the inside,
אינו דין שתהא מחשבה פוסלת בפנים? eino din shetehei machshava poseles bifnim?
So certainly your thought about bringing the blood on the inside should
invalidate the קרבן, korban, because the inside, when you actually bring the
blood, it invalidates the קרבן. korban, So your thought about the blood
should invalidate the קרבן. korban. חוץ לזמנו Chutz lizmano though? Well no,
חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. It's not חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. Right. But
the question is—well, that's the question—but why shouldn't it be logically? If
the actual bringing of blood—say it that way, it makes more sense—if
the actual bringing of blood invalidates and even more powerfully invalidates, the
thought of bringing the blood should also invalidate. הרי הוא אומר, Harei
hu omer, the verse says ביום השלישי. bayom hashlishi. Yeah, because where
we learn the idea, ironically, where we learn the idea of the
wrong place is a verse that says "third day," but we're going
to read that to mean "place." And the word three is critical.
Top of פב עמוד ב. Pei-beis amud-beis. מקום שהן משולש בדם בבשר
ובאימורין. Makom shehein meshulash bedam bevasar uveimurin. Only a place that is
tripled, i.e., has blood, meat, and the entrails, and not the inner
sanctum. So what does that mean? So the way רשי Rashi explains
what it means is: Outside of the מקדש, okay, when there at
least—or when there are במות—you're bamos allowed to do all those things.
The blood, the meat, and the entrails are all allowed outside the
מקדש. Whereas inside the היכל, heichal, okay, you're never allowed to do
anything other than blood. There's never an eating—you know, or maybe you
can eat the meat, but you're certainly—you never burn up the entrails
inside the היכל. heichal. So therefore it is not the same type
of place. It doesn't satisfy this criteria of משולש, meshulash, tripled, right?
And therefore
it is—your thought does not invalidate. Now you could have also said
the reverse. רשי Rashi says it's tripled that all three are good
outside, but all three are not good inside. You could have said
the reverse. Forget the time of במות. bamos. When there's a בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash blood, meat, and אימורין imurin are all invalidated when
you bring them outside. Now it is true, blood of שלמים shelamim
does not get invalidated when it's out of the עזרה, azarah, but
it does get invalidated when it's outside of its right zone. It's
out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So therefore thought invalidates on the outside, because
on the outside all those three things can get invalidated: blood, meat,
blood, meat, and אימורין. imurin. Whereas by a קרבן, korban if you
bring the blood on the inside, you invalidate it. But if you
bring the meat or the אימורין imurin into the היכל, heichal, you
don't invalidate them, okay? So this הלכה halacha that you can invalidate
a קרבן korban by bringing it more inside only applies to the
blood, right? Because it's again, because that means you're doing this ritual
which is an inner חטאת ritual. Okay. So therefore the thought does
not invalidate on the inside. Yes, the inside is more powerful when
it comes to the blood and invalidating the whole קרבן, korban, but
it's not basically an off-limits place, okay? The meat and the אימורין
imurin don't become invalid when you bring it there. So therefore thought
about the inside also does not invalidate. All right. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: ולא תהא מחשבה פוסלת בחוץ מקל וחומר.
Velo tehei machshava poseles bachutz mikal vachomer. All right, fine. So you're
going to tell me thought about the inside doesn't invalidate because it's
not משולש. meshulash. So fine. Now let's say thought about the outside
doesn't invalidate. ומה מקום שפסל דם שבפנים את שבחוץ אין מחשבה פוסלת
בפנים. Uma makom shepasal dam shebifnim es shebachutz ein machshava poseles bifnim.
On the inside, where it's more powerful, even a little blood invalidates
the whole קרבן, korban, but thought doesn't invalidate. מקום שלא פסל דם
שבחוץ את שבפנים. Makom shelo pasal dam shebachutz es shebifnim. The outside,
where a little bit of blood doesn't invalidate the rest, אינו דין
שלא תהא פוסלת מחשבה בחוץ? eino din shelo tehei poseles machshava bachutz?
Isn't it more—how much more so if thought doesn't invalidate on the
inside, so from a קל וחומר kal vachomer thought shouldn't invalidate on
the outside? תלמוד לומר שלישי. Talmud lomar shlishi. No. That's what we
learn from the extra word שלישי. shlishi. ביום השלישי, Bayom hashlishi, ironically,
although it's talking about day three,
that—I'm sorry, שלישי, shlishi, excuse me, שלישי, shlishi, חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano.
Now before we were using שלישי shlishi about מקום, makom, but here
we're using it about time. So שלישי shlishi is a thought about
the wrong time, which is the פשט pshat of the פסוק—well, pasuk,
the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is not a thought, but
the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is ביום השלישי, bayom hashlishi,
if it's the wrong time it invalidates. פיגול הוא. Pigul hu. The
extra word פיגול—this pigul is also ironic—חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. Because really
פיגול pigul is only a חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano thought, but it's
seen as an extra word פיגול, pigul, and that's coming to include
this place of the wrong place. So no, there is a הלכה
about a thought of a wrong place. So you combine the idea
that the word פיגול pigul is a thought of a wrong place,
the word שלישי shlishi tells you it has to be a place
that's משולש, meshulash, tripled, right? בשר, אימורין ודם. basar, imurin vedam. Okay,
so we're going to say that wrong place is outside the בית
המקדש, Beit Hamikdash and inside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. it is—a
thought does not invalidate because it's not this tripled place. place of
בשר, Bassar, אימורים, Emurim, and דם. Dam. Is that ironic? That a
thought on the inside does not invalidate even though the inside is
more invalidating when you bring blood in? Yes, it's ironic. But at
the end of the day, that's what the פסוקים psukim are telling
us. Okay, that thought, we know thought does invalidate wrong place because
of the word פיגול Pigul and the word שלוש, Shalosh, שלישי Shlishi
tells you only on the outside, not on the inside. Okay. Now.
Huh. Okay. בשר היוצא, Bassar hayotze, that's the end of going back
and forth about this קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you know, that רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili is pushing them that this is bizarre
that the inside is more invalidating than the outside. Now we're going
to say the following: בשר היוצא לחוץ פסול, הנכנס לפנים כשר. Bassar
hayotze lachutz passul, hanichnas lifnim kasher. Okay, now here's another הלכה, right?
Meat that goes outside is invalid. Meat that goes inside, this is
what we said before, it's not משולש בבשר, meshulash bevassar, right? Bringing
the meat into the היכל heichal does not invalidate it. Bringing the
meat out of the בית המקדש invalidates. The only thing that invalidates
in the היכל heichal is the blood. Okay. שהיה בדין שיפסול. Shehaya
badin sheyifsol. Logically you should say, if the inside is more invalidating
about blood, it should also be more invalidating about meat, right? If
the inside is more powerful as an invalidator than the outside when
it comes to blood, then certainly the same should be true about
meat. שהיה בדין שיפסול. Shehaya badin sheyifsol. ומה במקום שלא פסל דם
שבחוץ את שבפנים, בשר היוצא לחוץ פסול. Uma bimkom shelo passal dam
shebachutz et shebifnim, bassar hayotze lachutz passul. So when outside, which a
little bit of blood does not invalidate the rest, meat necessarily is
invalid when it's brought
outside. מקום שפסל דם שבפנים את שבחוץ, בשר הנכנס לפנים אינו דין
שיפסול? Makom shepassal dam shebifnim et shebachutz, bassar hanichnas lifnim eino din
sheyifsol? How much more so should meat brought inside invalidate? If the
inside is more powerful invalidator when it comes to blood, then it
should at least be as much of an invalidator when it comes
to meat. And meat brought inside should be פסול. passul. Okay, so
הרי הוא אומר, harei hu omer, מדמה. midamah. No. Because it says:
From its blood. דמה ולא בשר. Damah velo bassar. Only the blood
invalidates brought inside. It's a special הלכה. Blood, even some of the
blood. Yes, it's a unique הלכה, don't try to generalize. Okay, that
is the הלכה and it's only blood. Did you say also because
the inside is blood is the only validating item, so that it
could also be an invalidating item?
But meat... well meat wouldn't invalidate the whole קרבן, but the גמרא
Gemara is saying at least let the meat itself become פסול, passul,
so you couldn't eat the meat. No, I'm just saying like you
bringing the meat into the היכל, heichal, into the sanctuary, wouldn't serve
any, it doesn't validate anything. Right, right. What you're saying is what
I said before, is that it's not like the inside is a
bad place like the outside is a bad place. The problem with
the inside is not oh you took it in the wrong place.
The problem with bringing the blood on the inside is that you
were doing a ritual of an inner חטאת. Right, so right, once
you have that conceptual model everything makes sense. The whole, right, so
meat is not a process of making a קרבן. Right, I see,
because it also validates on the inside, it's the only thing that
can also validate. Correct, exactly. And therefore it can affect the whole
קרבן and that's why the power of bringing the blood is specific
to that. Right, and whereas bringing meat on the outside, it's not
about a ritual of validating or invalidating or whatever, it's just, it's
in the wrong place. So that's the basic explanation to all of
this. Is that the whole focus of wait this קל וחומר kal
vachomer is because you look at the inside as a bad place.
The inside isn't a bad place. The inside is, you're bringing the
blood there, you're doing a ritual that normally is a ritual of
validating an inner קרבן and you're doing this ritual for a different
קרבן, so you're messing things up because of this ritual. That's the
problem. The problem is not that it's a bad place. Okay, so
it says like this. It says,
okay, so מדמה. midamah. Okay, דמה ולא בשר. damah velo bassar. קל
וחומר מעתה. Kal vachomer me'ata.
But the גמרא Gemara. again does not give up on its model.
ומה במקום שפסל דם שבפנים את שבחוץ, בשר הנכנס לפנים כשר. Uma
bimkom shepassal dam shebifnim et shebachutz, bassar hanichnas lifnim kasher. Fine.
So now you're going to say, the inside, which is a powerful
invalidator of blood, doesn't invalidate meat. So let's say the same about
the outside. Okay. מקום שלא פסל דם שבחוץ את שבפנים. Makom shelo
passal dam shebachutz et shebifnim.
How about when a little bit of the place that a little
bit of blood doesn't invalidate the rest, the outside, so the outside
is not as powerful of an invalidator because it doesn't invalidate all
the blood, okay, בשר היוצא לחוץ אינו דין שיהא כשר? bassar hayotze
lachutz eino din sheyehe kasher? So the meat should remain כשר kasher
when it's brought on the outside. If the meat remains כשר kasher
brought on the inside, the meat should remain כשר when it's brought
on the outside. No, we learn that from a verse. ובשר בשדה
טריפה לא תאכלו. Uvassar bassadeh tereifah lo socheilu.
Now this is not about a קרבן, but conceptually we're going to
say that any meat that is בשדה, bassadeh, it's the concept of
a שדה sadeh is an unbound place. It's in a place that's
not maintaining its boundaries. That becomes unedible. Okay, it's like a טריפה
tereifah and can't be eaten. כיון שיצא בשר חוץ ממחיצתו נאסר. Keivan
sheyatza bassar chutz mimchitzato ne'essar.
So that's where we learn that the meat becomes invalid. Okay. So,
the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara learns it all from פסוקים,
pesukim, but at the end of the day, it's like David is
saying is that it is not that if you think of it
like good place bad place, so it's ironic. Oh, the inside is
a worse place by blood, it should also be a worse place
by meat, it should also invalidate by thought and blah blah blah.
But if it's not about being a bad place, I mean, it's
you're getting into the, it's even more in the בית המקדש. How
could it be a bad place? What it's about is doing a
wrong ritual, okay? And therefore it's limited to blood and limited to
bringing it when its purpose is לכפר בקודש. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, Rabbis taught, פנימה, pnima, אין לי אלא פנימה,
ein li ela pnima, I only know when you bring it all
the way inside. פנימה pnima is like the inner chamber, the קודש
קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. היכל מנין, Heichal minayin, how do I know if
you bring it in just to the היכל, Heichal, right? Where the
ארון Aron and the מנורה Menorah and the שולחן Shulchan are but
not into the קודש קדשים? Kodesh Kodashim? So הרי מנין תלמוד לומר
אל הקודש פנימה. harei minayin talmud lomar el hakodesh pnima. The extra
word קודש Kodesh is to tell you even if it's not all
the way פנימה, pnima, it's just אל הקודש. el hakodesh. That's enough.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says ויאמר קודש ואל יאמר פנימה.
viyomar Kodesh v'al yomar pnima. So just say אל הקודש. el hakodesh.
If I know that it's invalid, you know, by the היכל, Heichal,
certainly it would be invalid when you get it to the קודש
קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Why did it have to say פנימה, pnima, just
say קודש? Kodesh? So אמר רבא בזה ולימד על זה. amar Rava
bazeh velimmed al zeh. No, because if it had just said קודש,
Kodesh, I would have read קודש Kodesh to mean קודש קדשים. Kodesh
Kodashim. But once I have an extra word פנימה, pnima, which means
קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, now I know that the word קודש Kodesh
means even the היכל. Heichal. Okay, so the reason it could have
just said קודש Kodesh if it would have been clear that קודש
Kodesh meant היכל. Heichal. But קודש Kodesh is a little bit of
a vague word. So the only way I get to know that
it means היכל Heichal is because of the extra word פנימה pnima
which means the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. All right, clear? So מידי
דהוה איתושב ושכיר, midi dehava atoshav vesachir, like we have in another
place that we have some vague words and it says two of
them and therefore I learn even the weaker case. But I needed
both so I knew we were talking about the weaker case. What
is this? It says a תושב ושכיר toshav vesachir of a כהן
Kohen cannot eat קודש, Kodesh, cannot eat תרומה. terumah. So a slave,
עבד כנעני Eved Kna'ani can, but a hired hand like a תושב,
toshav, an indentured servant cannot. Who's the indentured servant of the תורה?
Torah? Not the עבד כנעני, Eved Kna'ani, not the non-Jewish slave, but
the עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, the Jewish slave. Okay, so a Jewish
slave cannot eat from the תרומה terumah of a כהן Kohen because
the כהן Kohen doesn't fully own him. And the תושב ושכיר toshav
vesachir is going to talk about two types of Jewish slaves. What
are the two types
of Hebrew slaves?
The one who works for six years and the permanent one who's
permanent until the יובל. Yovel. So even the one who's permanent until
the יובל, Yovel, he's freed at the יובל, Yovel, so he's not
fully owned. So even he is not like the עבד כנעני Eved
Kna'ani and he's not totally the property of a כהן Kohen and
he does not eat תרומה. terumah. So that's what תושב ושכיר toshav
vesachir are telling me. Okay, so let's take a look. מידי דהוה
איתושב ושכיר, midi dehava atoshav vesachir, דתניא, detanya, תושב זה קנוי קניין
עולם toshav zeh kanui kinyan olam because תושב toshav means like settled.
So he's here forever. Now again, ever, I mean ever is the
word in the פסוק, ועבדו לעולם, v'avadu le'olam, but he'll go free
in the יובל. Yovel. Okay, that's one type of Hebrew slave. Okay,
שכיר, sachir, which obviously has a sense of less settled, he's a
hired hand. Okay, זה קנוי קניין שנים. zeh kanui kinyan shanim.
That's somebody that you is just for six years. Now ולימא תושב
ולא לימא שכיר, velima toshav velo lima sachir, just tell me even
a תושב toshav can't eat תרומה, terumah, isn't considered the property of
a כהן, Kohen, and of course I would say that a slave
of six years doesn't eat תרומה. terumah. ואני אומר, va'ani omer, קנוי
קניין עולם אינו אוכל, kanui kinyan olam eino ochel, if somebody who's
permanently owned can't eat תרומה, terumah, קנוי קניין שנים לא כל שכן,
kanui kinyan shanim lo kol sheken, how much somebody who's only owned
for six years can't eat תרומה? terumah? So why didn't it just
say
תושב? toshav? So אילו כן, ilu ken, because had it just said
תושב, toshav, הייתי אומר, hayiti omer, I would have said תושב זה
קנוי קניין שנים. toshav zeh kanui kinyan shanim. I would have read
it in a more limited way. I wouldn't have known תושב toshav
meant the more extreme case. I would have said תושב toshav meant
the guy for six years, אבל קנוי קניין עולם יהא אוכל. aval
kanui kinyan olam yehe ochel. I would have thought that a guy
who's owned for the יובל Yovel could eat. בא שכיר ולימד על
תושב, ba sachir velimmed al toshav, שזה קנוי קניין עולם וזה קנוי
קניין שנים, shezeh kanui kinyan olam vezeh kanui kinyan shanim, ואינו אוכל.
ve'eino ochel.
So שכיר sachir teaches me the lighter case, the case of being
held for six years. So then I'm left with explaining the word
תושב toshav to mean the guy who's owned for until the יובל
Yovel and even he cannot eat the תרומה. terumah. Okay?
So therefore here too, if it would have just said קודש, Kodesh,
I would have said it meant קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. It had
to say פנימה, pnima, so now I understand that the word קודש
Kodesh means even the היכל. Heichal. Okay, that's what רבא Rava says.
So that's a pretty good answer. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye,
אביי Abaye didn't like this answer. Why not? Seems pretty good. You're
right, in the end one is superfluous, but it teaches me what
the other one means. No, אביי Abaye said בשלמא התם תרי גופי
נינהו. bishlama hatam trei gufei ninhu. There
they're two different people. There's a תושב toshav and there's a שכיר.
sachir. So אף על גב דהוה ליה לקרא למיכתב נרצע לא יאכל.
af al gav dehava lei leikra lemichtav nirtza lo yochel. Now, you
it's true, the תורה Torah could have been because the point is,
don't tell me oh, it used the word
תושב toshav I wouldn't have known what it meant, so it had
to say שכיר. sachir. It didn't have to say שכיר. sachir. You
know how else it could have told me what it meant? It
could have been more explicit.
It could have said נרצה. nirtza. Okay? So אביי Abaye says it's
not enough to say oh, it was a vague term I needed
another term, because just use a more explicit term. Why did the
Torah not say the word נרצה, nirtza, the guy who has had
his, you know, his ear punched? So ואידך אתי בקל וחומר, veidach
ati bekal vachomer, and I would have learned out the other guy
from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So I could have been more
explicit. But at the end of the day, it's not so bad
that it says both. Why?
Because מילתא דאתי בקל וחומר טרח וכתב לה קרא. milta deati bekal
vachomer tarach vechatav lah kra.
Since at the end of the day, it's two different people, I
could say, you know what? The Torah had a choice. It could
have said נרצה, nirtza, and I would have figured out the six-year
slave based on a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. But at the end
of the day, it's still telling me, there're both of these slaves
and this הלכה applies to this category of slave and that category
of slave. So even though it's a little bit extra, sometimes things
I could have inferred the Torah's going to tell me explicitly. Okay,
that makes sense there. Why doesn't it make sense here? Because here,
he's going to say look, why didn't the Torah just explicitly tell
me אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, right? It could rather than use a
vague term קדש. Kodesh. Say אהל מועד Ohel Moed and I would
have known it meant the היכל. Heichal. Now, you're going to tell
me, okay, you could have learned it from a קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, but it wanted to tell you קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. But
no says אביי, Abaye, there's no way you're going to get to
bring it into the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim without first traversing the
היכל. Heichal. So it's one thing to say it applies to this
category of slave and that category of slave and maybe I could
have inferred it, but at the end of the day, they're different
people, and it's both true about this person and true about that
person. But here, the Torah should have been explicit, said אהל מועד,
Ohel Moed, and I don't need to tell me it also applies
to the קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. You know why? Because it doesn't
even apply to the קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, because you've already invalidated
it as soon as you've brought it into the היכל. Heichal. So
you don't it's not even true about the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim
that it's a source of invalidity. The invalidity happened already. Okay. אלא
הכא כיון דאפסל בהיכל לפני ולפנים מאי בעי? ela hacha keivan deifsal
beheichal lifnai velifnim mai ba'ei? It already became פסול pasul in the
היכל. Heichal. לפני ולפנים מאי בעי? lifnai velifnim mai ba'ei? It's there's
not an invalidity, no invalidity is caused by the קדש קדשים. Kodesh
Kodashim. So I don't get it says אביי. Abaye. It's not I
don't get
why it needed both words, as why does the Torah altogether, you
know, give the case of the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim if it's
already invalidated by the היכל? Heichal? אלא אמר אביי לא נצרכה אלא
דרך משובש. ela amar Abaye lo nitzrecha ela derech meshubash. I'll tell
you a case where you could get the invalidity of the קדש
קדשים Kodesh Kodashim without exactly without that of the היכל. Heichal. You
do it in a roundabout way. You take some you go through
to the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim through the attic. Okay? So that's
why. So in the end he agrees to רבא. Rava. It needed
to tell me both of them are true. I could have learned
it from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, and it said both words,
even though I could have learned it from a קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, because by saying פנימה pnima I learned that קדש Kodesh meant
the היכל. Heichal. So in the end he agrees to רבא. Rava.
I could have learned it from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. He's
only clarifying that the reason by saying קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, how
is that not also a case of היכל? Heichal? And his answer
is, there's a way you could go straight into the קדש קדשים.
Kodesh Kodashim. אמר ליה רבא, amar leh Rava, רבא Rava said back,
now that you're raising that question, that how do you get קדש
קדשים Kodesh Kodashim that isn't straight a case of היכל, Heichal, I'm
not happy with your answer. He said והובא כתיב אשר יובא מדמה
vehuva ktiv asher yuva midama and יובא מדמה yuva midama means brought
in the natural way. So we're back to your question אביי. Abaye.
Forget why the פסוק had to say both. Your real question is
fine, it said both to clarify what the word קדש Kodesh meant.
Whatever, it doesn't matter. Your real question is, what does it mean
that the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim invalidates? It never gets there before
it's already invalidated, and don't tell me you went through the roof,
okay, because you know because because הובא huva means brought naturally. What's
the Beatles song? Came in through the bathroom window? Okay, אלא אמר
רבא, ela amar Rava, so rather רבא Rava said, כל מידי דחשיב
עליה לפני ולפנים לא מיפסל בהיכל. kol midi dechashiv aleih lifnai velifnim
lo mipsal beheichal.
I'll tell you how it becomes פסול pasul in the קדש קדשים
Kodesh Kodashim and not in the היכל. Heichal. You remember it says
אשר יובא מדמה לכפר בקדש. asher yuva midama lechaper bakodesh. It matters
what your intent is. So רבא Rava says if your intent is
to bring it and sprinkle it let's say on the ארון, Aron,
to sprinkle it in the קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, your intent is
not to sprinkle it in the היכל. Heichal. Your intent is the
קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim alone, then when you bring it into the
היכל Heichal it doesn't become invalidated. It only becomes invalidated when you
get it to the קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So yes, קדש קדשים
Kodesh Kodashim can serve as an independent source of invalidity. It doesn't
always become invalidated just when you bring it in because you need
your thought to be linked. And if your thought is not about
the היכל Heichal and your thought is about the קדש קדשים, Kodesh
Kodashim, the היכל Heichal does not invalidate. Okay. You're not allowed to
do that except on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Right, but the question
is not whether you were allowed, the question was whether it invalidates.
Okay.
בעי רבא, ba'ei Rava, now רבא Rava asks the following. פר העלם
דבר של ציבור ושעיר עבודת כוכבים. par helam davar shel tzibur vesaeir
avodat kochavim. Here are two things that are inner חטאות. chata'ot. פר
par of יום כיפור Yom Kippur and the שעיר saeir of עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. So they are already inner חטאות. chata'ot. שהכניס דמן
לפני ולפנים מהו? shehichnis daman lifnai velifnim mahu?
I'm sorry. But here's the thing. While they're an inner חטאת, what
they are not is ושעיר עבודת כוכבים. v'Sa'ir Avodas Kochavim. I'm sorry,
I think I said יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. I didn't mean יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. I meant עבודת כוכבים. Avodas Kochavim. Okay. These things
as opposed to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, by יום כיפור Yom Kippur
the blood goes into the קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kadashim. By the two
other inner חטאות chata'ot that are not יום כיפור Yom Kippur related,
which is פר העלם דבר של ציבור Par He'elem Davar shel Tzibbur
and the שעיר עבודת זרה, Sa'ir Avodat Zarah, the goat of עבודת
זרה, Avodat Zarah, those two which are inner but don't go into
the- they don't go into the Holy of Holies. Only the יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, right, that's the whole power of יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, right? לא יבוא בכל עת אל הקדש בזאת יבוא אהרן אל
הקדש, Lo yavo be-chol eis el ha-kodesh be-zos yavo Aharon el ha-kodesh,
only on יום כיפור Yom Kippur do you bring blood into the
Holy of Holies. Okay, so these two are inner חטאות, chata'ot, but
they don't go into the Holy of Holies. What would be if
you brought their blood into the Holy of Holies? Would that invalidate?
This could be another cute, nice example of where the קדש קדשים
Kodesh Kadashim
invalidates and the היכל Heichal does not. You got it? The blood
goes into the היכל, Heichal, it's supposed to go into the היכל
Heichal and you bring it into the קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kadashim, do
you invalidate? That would be a source for this idea that the
קדש קדשים Kodesh Kadashim is a basis of invalidating. So, he says
like this: שהכניס דמם לפני ולפנים מהו. She-hechnis damam lifnai velifnim mahu.
מי אמרינן אל הקדש פנימה כל היכא דקרינן אל הקדש קרינן ליה
פנימה? Mi amrinan el ha-kodesh pnima kol heicha de-karinan el ha-kodesh karinan
lei pnima? Maybe only something that's invalid if brought in the היכל
Heichal can be invalid if brought in the קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kadashim.
כל היכא דלא קרינן אל הקדש, Kol heicha de-lo karinan el ha-kodesh,
some place where it's not wrong to bring it into the היכל,
Heichal, you're supposed to bring the blood into the היכל Heichal because
it's an inner חטאת, לא קרינן פנימה, lo karinan pnima, do we
say it doesn't get invalidated when you bring it into the Holy
of Holies? או דלמא שלא במקומן הוא, O dilma she-lo bimkomon hu,
or do we say no, at the end of the day this
is not their right place, this is too inner and if it's
too inner you would invalidate it even by an inner חטאת. Good
question. Okay. ואם תמצא לומר שלא במקומן הוא, Ve-im timtza lomar she-lo
bimkomon hu, now let's say you say yeah, you would invalidate an
inner חטאת if you brought their blood into the Holy of Holies.
So here's my next question: פר ושעיר של יום הכפורים, Par ve-se'ir
shel Yom HaKippurim, you actually are dealing with יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
the blood is already brought in the Holy of Holies. שהזה מדמן
על הבדים והוציאן להיכל, She-hizah mi-damam al ha-badim ve-hotzi'an la-heichal, you did
it on the- on the ארון Aron and then what do you
do after you do the ארון? Aron? You take it out and
you're supposed to put it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, on the
פרוכת paroches and then on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So you left the
Holy of Holies and now והכניסן, ve-hichnisan, you went back in. You
said, 'You know what? I'm going to do it again back in-
back on the ארון. Aron. I liked it so much being there
with the ארון, Aron, I'm going back in.' Maybe he didn't think
he did it right? Maybe he didn't think he did it right.
Anyway, so there you brought it more inner than it was- it
was no longer entitled to go inside, but it was blood that
actually a minute ago, that's where it belonged. That's not really an
off-sides place of the blood. Okay. So, והוציאן והכניסן מהו? ve-hotzi'an ve-hichnisan
mahu?
What do we say? מי אמרינן מקומן הוא, Mi amrinan mekomon hu,
at the end of the day the inside is a proper place
for this blood, the Holy of Holies. או דלמא הוי נפיק נפיק,
O dilma hovei nefik nefik, since the blood went out, it's now
out and it doesn't get to go back in, and going back
in is bringing it, you know, is bringing it too much inside.
Let's finish this up. Now, ואם תמצא לומר הוי נפיק נפיק, ve-im
timtza lomar hovei nefik nefik, if you say no, once it's brought
outside it's brought outside, end of story, and if you bring it
in you invalidate. So if that's true, so then here's the final
question. Okay. Hold on a second.
I'm sorry, just have somebody waiting for me. Okay, here's the final
question: הזה מדמן על הפרוכת והוציאו למזבח. Hizah mi-damam al ha-paroches ve-hotzi'o
la-mizbe'ach.
So you sprinkled on- it's יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you sprinkled on
the פרוכת, paroches, on the curtain, and then it says ויצא אל
המזבח, ve-yatza el ha-mizbe'ach, right? So if this is the היכל, Heichal,
right, and this part you went in the Holy of Holies, you
came out, you sprinkled on the curtain, here's the מזבח הזהב mizbe'ach
ha-zahav and it says you go out, meaning you don't stay in
the inner part, you go around so you're on the outer part
of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And the Torah refers to going to the
מזבח mizbe'ach with the word והוציא, ve-hotzi, to bring it out. Now,
the Bible scholars will say פשט pshat of the פסוק really means
you bring the blood to the outer מזבח mizbe'ach because the word
והוציא ve-hotzi sounds like that. But the גמרא Gemara says that no,
the משנה Mishnah says that והוציא ve-hotzi means just the מזבח הזהב.
mizbe'ach ha-zahav. Since it's referred to as הוציא, hotzi, so maybe that
calls it an outer place. And now, if you bring it back,
not even into the Holy of Holies, just more inner, is that
now considered bringing the blood to an inner place and it invalidates
it? והכניסן מהו? Ve-hichnisan mahu? הכא בר חד מקום הוא? Hacha barei
chad makom hu? Do we say no, at the end of the
day it's all- it's all one place and therefore it's not like
קדש, kodesh, היכל, Heichal, עזרה, azaroh, those are different places. Outside of
the golden altar and inner to the golden altar is not really
a different place. או דלמא, O dilma, or do we say יציאה
קרינן ביה, yatzeinan karinan bei, since the Torah says outside, so therefore
it means that this is considered outer, and if you brought it
back more inner, that would be like bringing it into a different
place and an inner place and you would invalidate it. And the
גמרא concludes תיקו. teiku. We're not going to know, we don't know.
All very good questions, okay.